<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of a new league made by the Emperour of Germany, with other princes, potentates and states Catholicke, against the enemies of the Roman Catholick-Religion, with the names of those princes As also, the true numbers, both of horse and foot, which euery one of them offereth to set forward so great a designe. Vnto which is added the copie of a letter sent by the King of Spaine to Pope Vrbine the 8. printed according the Spanish copie set forth at Madrill. Vnto all which is likewise added: The discouerie of a New Spanish Armado, threatning with fire and sword to inuade England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115035</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850254</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15443</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15443)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of a new league made by the Emperour of Germany, with other princes, potentates and states Catholicke, against the enemies of the Roman Catholick-Religion, with the names of those princes As also, the true numbers, both of horse and foot, which euery one of them offereth to set forward so great a designe. Vnto which is added the copie of a letter sent by the King of Spaine to Pope Vrbine the 8. printed according the Spanish copie set forth at Madrill. Vnto all which is likewise added: The discouerie of a New Spanish Armado, threatning with fire and sword to inuade England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mercurius Britannicus,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The copie of a letter from the Catholicke Majestie of our Lord the King, to our holy father the Pope, Vrbane the VIII" has caption title on B4r.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank?.</note>
                  <note>The Folger copy has an extra quire, E4, with the Spanish: Relacion de la liga.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-D4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic League, 1609-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15443:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15443:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF A NEW <hi>LEAG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> MADE BY THE EMPEROVR of GERMANY, with other Princes, Potentates and States <hi>Catholicke,</hi> againſt the Enemies of the <hi>Roman</hi> CATHOLICK-RELIGION, <hi>WITH The Names of thoſe Princes.</hi> AS ALSO, The true Numbers, both of Horſe and Foot, which euery one of them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth to ſet forward ſo great a Deſigne. <hi>Vnto which is added the Copie of a Letter ſent by the King of</hi> Spaine <hi>to Pope</hi> VRBINE <hi>the</hi> 8. Printed according the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Copie ſet forth at <hi>Madrill. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto all which is likewiſe added:</hi> The Diſcouerie of a New <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado, threatning with Fire and Sword to Inuade ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Mercurius Britannicus.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:15443:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15443:2"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF THE League, <hi>made by the Emperour of Germany,</hi> with other Princes, Potentates, and States <hi>Catholicke,</hi> againſt the Enemies of the <hi>Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick-Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Noueltie of ſo high a nature as this is, (in which all <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> or the greateſt part of it, ſtandeth intereſſed) ſhould not Preſent it ſelfe to the world, without the Noble at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance of Probabilitie and Poſſibilitie, the one to confirme the Truth, the other to enable the Action: Both which (to cleere vnderſtanding eyes) are Wayters vpon this.</p>
            <p>For if wee conſider the Hate which the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and his Colleagues beare to our Kingdome; It is a likelihood ſufficient to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15443:3"/>perſwades vs, that he is preparing Forces: and if we looke, but vpon his <hi>Indian</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, his Commaund ouer ſeuerall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, his Armies in ſeuerall places, and the deſires which his Subiects haue to ſet footing in our Countrey, wee may finde ſtrong arguments of his Poſſibilitie, to begin an Inuaſion, or any attempt elſe.</p>
            <p>But becauſe our Nation, are not apt to feare any Spaniſh danger (how lowd ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſpeakes) vnleſſe they heare it roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at their doores; It will bee no great loſſe of time, to liſten to this ſhort Storie, which the <hi>Spaniard</hi> relates (to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) in his owne haughty Language.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="account">
                        <head>The Spaniſh Relation.</head>
                        <p>BLeſſings from Heauen, and good wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes on Earth, be euer attendant on All thoſe, who are zealous in the ſeruice of GOD, and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Common-good: as alſo, on this League Vnited together by the Emperor, and celebrated with all the Rites in <hi>Bruſſels</hi> before the moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15443:3"/>INFANTA, both in regard of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, which her <hi>Altezza</hi> (or Highnes) hath in that Citie, as alſo, for the Scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, honor, and commodity of the place.</p>
                        <p>And albeit, I am well aſſured, that his Imperiall Maieſtie, hath with much deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration and wiſdome, made tryall in his Iudgement of all thoſe things which are comprehended in this League; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding (as well to ſatisfie my ſelfe as to diſcharge the duty belonging to my place, which I hold vnder his Catholicke Maieſtie) I will briefly ſet downe my knowledge in this great Buſineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe happily, ſome may gather the fruit of experience from it, as the Bee ſuckes Honey out of a bitter Flower.</p>
                        <p>Firſt then, it hath bin held a matter of great importance, that in this League ſhould bee comprehended, his Holineſſe, the Maieſties Imperiall and Catholicke, all the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Catholick Electors, all the chiefe Princes, Potentates, and Republickes Catholicke, in <hi>Germany, Italy, Flaunders, &amp;c.</hi> well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the <hi>Sea Apoſtolicall,</hi> and to their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15443:4"/>Maieſties. Herein ſhewing a deſire to ſow Peace, Quietneſſe and Iuſtice, amongſt all thoſe States, ouer which God hath placed them, thereby to eſtabliſh a new League euerlaſting and hereditary, as Friends to Friends, and Enemies to Enemies, with Penall clauſes and other neceſſary Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that this League ſhould bee publiſhed and declared by Ambaſſadors or Agents, (Ordinary or Extraordinary) to all other Kings, Princes, Potentates, and States, which are Friends, albeit not well affected, or being of another Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For this muſt worke one of theſe two Things; either they muſt ſend to this Diet (or Aſſembly) and enter as the reſt doe into the League vpon the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; or if they refuſe ſo to doe, then are they to bee excluded and barred from any benefit which by the League may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and ſo bee branded with the Notes, markes, and blemiſhes of Obſtinacy, and euill Hearts, they of the League hereby hauing juſt cauſe giuen them, to beware of ſuch people.</p>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15443:4"/>
                        <p>Concerning Trade and Commerce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe of the League, their Friends, Subiects and Vaſſals; the ſame libertie ſhall bee giuen them which heretofore they haue had without Exception, and without any new Cuſtomes, Impoſitions or other Duties, than thoſe neceſſary Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which muſt be diſpended to fight againſt Rebels and knowne Enemies.</p>
                        <p>What Occurrent, fact, or difference ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall happen betweene any of the Colleagued Princes, or any of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; it ſhall bee ended and taken vp by the Soueraigne Prince to whom the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement thereof doth appertaine, or by him, who with conſent of the reſt of the League, or the major part, ſhall be held fit to decide it: and what ſentence hee ſets downe ſhall peremptorily ſtand, vpon paine of being Expulſed from the Societie of the League, or to feele the ſharpneſſe of their Indignation.</p>
                        <p>The Pope, Emperor, euery King, Prince, Potentate, and State, which enters into this League, ſhall giue the Number of ſuch Forces (Horſe and Foot) which wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15443:5"/>they intend to furniſh; aſwell thoſe which they haue already raiſed, and paide in their owne Kingdomes and Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as of any other Troupes, which they are to raiſe with all expedition and at their proper Charges, vpon any occaſion whatſoeuer, to the due obſeruance of the League, which is confederated together for Three ſpeciall ends.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 <hi>The first, to Conſerue Peace, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Amitie, amongst the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues, and to Chaſtiſe any one that falls off, and doth not accompliſh what hee promiſeth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2 <hi>The ſecond, to prevent, curbe and bridle any other Prince, (albeit not one of the League) whenſoever hee offers to Invade, directly or indirectly, any of the Confederate Princes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3 <hi>Thirdly, to make quicke Warre vpon the Common Enemy, as Rebels, Turkes, Moores, Tartars, &amp;c. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15443:5"/>there bee a generall Conſent ſo to haue it done.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now, to ſhow, that for euery Prince to deliuer vp the Number of all ſuch men, as hee hath already leauyed and payed, (or the greater part of them) can bee to him no danger or loſſe, but rather a moſt aſſured ſafetie and profit. And it is firſt to be conſidered, that none of them can receiue any harme, ſeeing they haue the like intereſt whether they maintaine their men within or without their State. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, concerning the perill, it is certaine that leauying in their ordinary Garriſons, for the time that may be neceſſary ſome expert Commanders, and diuers skilfull Souldiers, which euer any Prince vſed to haue without pay onely for his defence, they cannot therefore runne into any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill or danger.</p>
                        <p>Now, for the third point which is Safetie, It is plaine, that whenſoeuer any Stranger ſhall attempt to wrong any of the Confederated Princes, who punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally haue deliuered all or part of ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15443:6"/>Forces as by them are leauyed; It is moſt certaine (and ſo reſolued vpon) that All the reſt ſhall take his part, and defend him by ſuch meanes, as in their beſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall be held fit.</p>
                        <p>Hereupon it is inferred, that if in the beginning of thoſe troubles and Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which ſet <hi>Germany, Flaunders, Italy,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> on fire, there had beene ſuch another League with a ready and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Intelligence paſſing betweene thoſe Chriſtian Princes, which were truely juſt, and religiouſly giuen; Then, it had kept the <hi>Germanes</hi> from Revolting, the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians, Tranſilvanians, Hollanders,</hi> and <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate</hi> from Rebelling; neither, had the <hi>Venetians</hi> euer ſo much as dreamed of an Inuaſion to bee made vpon the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Townes; no, nor had the <hi>Savoyans</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> put on Armes firſt againſt <hi>Mantua,</hi> and then againſt <hi>Genoa,</hi> woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (in both theſe times) the Subiects of his Catholicke Maieſtie; Neither, had the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Venetians,</hi> ſpotted their Names with ſuch infamous reproaches, for Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from his Holines the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15443:6"/>vpon the Accord, and ingagement of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King himſelfe, was deliuered vp in truſt to the hands of his Holines: Nay more, thoſe other infinite Inſolencies, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledges, and Inhumanities (which for modeſties ſake I bury in ſilence) had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene ſo barbarouſly committed, to the ſhedding of ſo much Innocent blood, the loſſe of ſo much wealth, and vtter ruine of ſo much noble Reputation.</p>
                        <p>Great hope therefore there is, that ſuch a number of Chriſtian Princes, entring together into this Holy League, there will follow not onely an amendment of Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes paſt, but a preuention of many Euils to come. It being held for certaine, that when this League is fully publiſhed and made knowne, all the Oppoſites againſt it, ſhall neuer bee able to beget a ſecond Combination (amongſt themſelues) of ſufficient Power to conteſt or contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Fourth part of this.</p>
                        <list>
                           <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15443:7"/>
                           <head>Here followeth the Number both of the Foot and Horſe, (Infantry and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallerie) leauyed and ſet foorth by the vnder-named Princes.</head>
                           <item>THe Pope in regard of the Churches E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, doth offer 1000. Horſe, and 8000. Foot.</item>
                           <item>The Emperor, in regard of all his States 4000. Horſe, and 20000 Foot.</item>
                           <item>The Catholick King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in regard of all his Command in <hi>Spaine, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> 8000. Horſe, 20000. Foot.</item>
                           <item>The King of <hi>Poland,</hi> 2000. Horſe, and 4000. Foot.</item>
                           <item>The Archduke <hi>Leopold,</hi> 500. Horſe, and 3000. Foot.</item>
                           <item>The Elector of <hi>Colleyne,</hi> 500 horſe, and 3000 foot.</item>
                           <item>The Elector of <hi>Mentz,</hi> 500. horſe, and 400. foot.</item>
                           <item>The Elector of <hi>Trever,</hi> 500. horſe, and 3000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>Baviere,</hi> 400. horſe, and 3000. foot.</item>
                           <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15443:7"/>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> (who is a Friend) 400. Horſe, and 3000. Foot.</item>
                           <item>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Sarzburg,</hi> 300. horſe and 1000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>Newburg,</hi> 500. horſe, and 2000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The great Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> 1000. horſe and 3000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> 300. horſe, and 1000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> 300. horſe, and 1000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> 300. horſe, and 1000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The Duke of <hi>Vrbine,</hi> 300. horſe, and 1000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The State of <hi>Genoa,</hi> 1000. horſe, and 4000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The State of <hi>Luca,</hi> 300. horſe, and 1000. foot.</item>
                           <item>The <hi>Cantons</hi> Catholicke of the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> 2000. Horſe.</item>
                           <item>Which in all amount to 22100. Horſe, and 87000. Foot: a number ſufficient to worke all the Effects before treated.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>But if at any time, occcaſion ſhould call
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15443:8"/>for a greater Army, euery Prince is to bring in his proportionable number, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former agreement.</p>
                        <p>So that vpon any juſt cauſe, euery Prince muſt ſend in his quantity of Artillerie, Munition, &amp; all other things neceſſary fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe numbers, which he furniſheth.</p>
                        <p>Then, that his Holineſſe, with thoſe Kings and Princes, who are furniſhed with Gallies, Ships, or other Defences by Sea, ſhall bee ready with them vpon any occaſion offered, according to that Rate to which they binde themſelues.</p>
                        <p>Alſo, that the Princes of the League ſhall with one conſent (aduiſedly to be taken) Elect a Generall out of all this aſſembly, who ſhall bee a man of Qualitie, Valour, and Experience ſufficient.</p>
                        <p>By this meanes, the diuine Maieſtie will aſſiſt and Crowne this holy Enterpriſe, It tending only to his glory and the Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his holy Name; as alſo, for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Peace and Concord, of the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world, and withall to Bridle and Confound all malicious, turbulent, and ill-affected Spirits.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
                  <back>
                     <div type="colophon">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Printed at</hi> Seuill <hi>with Authority, by</hi> Simon Fajardo, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                  </back>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15443:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Copie of a Letter from the Catholicke Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of our Lord the King, to our holy Father the Pope,</hi> VRBANE <hi>the</hi> VIII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HOly Father:</hi> I receiued your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the 12. of the laſt Moneth, which your Holineſſe ſent me by the Poſt who came from <hi>Vrbine</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to <hi>Millane.</hi> In anſwer of which, I ſay, that before I receiued them, I was well aduertiſed &amp; ſufficiently informed, of all the Nouelties therin ſet downe, and of all thoſe things which are comprehended in the League; for they haue beene many dayes about it, to mold it, and reduce it into Forme, (as in my writings dated the 6. of Nouember,) I haue made it appeare to your Holines. Let them performe the beſt of their power, &amp; doe what they can, yet your Holineſſe knowes, that God is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to effect much more: and I for my part (his diuine Arme aſſiſting me) will (as I am bound) doe my vtmoſt in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Catholick Faith, as my Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers haue done before me.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Millane</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> I haue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my Gouernors to joyne their Forces,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15443:9"/>to diuert the Intentions of thoſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes which liue there, and to appoint the Rendevous in the State of <hi>Millane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bee your Holineſſe aſſured, that if you haue occaſion to vſe them, you may; for albeit, I giue no Cauſe to haue warre made vpon me, yet (though their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers be but ſmall) they haue good hearts, ſo that God in behalfe of the Church, will be on their ſide and aſſiſt them.</p>
            <p>The Horſe and Foot amount to 80000. men, and if this bee not ſufficient, I haue giuen order to the Duke of <hi>Feria,</hi> to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe me with ſpeed, who inſtantly and perſonally ſhall haſten to mend it; albeit it bee done with a ſmall number of Men, part of them to bee leauyed out of theſe Kingdomes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which ſhall riſe to 80000. more.</p>
            <p>By this meanes your Holineſſe may both ſee &amp; know the Obedience of ſuch a Sonne, and I the way to ſerue ſo holy a Father, whom God proſper, and guard, for the Augmentation of the Holy Faith as the Catholicke Church hath need, and I deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Madrid,</hi> &amp;c.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:15443:9"/>
            <p>THus farre our warlike Newes, of Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Vnitings ſo many Princes in a Holy League (as themſelues Chriſten it) has betrayed it ſelfe to you in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which ſo perfectly and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly before ſpake nothing but Spaniſh.</p>
            <p>And to ſtrengthen this Report, here is another Confirmation ſent by a friend out of Spaine, to his acquaintance in London, in this manner.</p>
            <p>Sir, albeit I make no doubt but that the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary preparations of the Spaniſh Fleet, are by Letters arriued in England, yet by reaſon of the frequent houering of the Spaniſh here in Marſeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, I preſume, you cannot meete a more exact knowledge of the Particulars, then theſe which I ſend you, holding my ſelfe bound to acquaint you with the Truth.</p>
            <p>The certaine place of their intended Inuaſion, is not publiſhed; but common muttering whiſpers in our Eares, that it is for England, Ireland, and the Netherlands, yet ſome ſuſpect, it is againſt the Venetians. But leauing that, be pleaſed to caſt your Eye on theſe Particulars following, which are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted here for truths, and ſo we receiue them.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Galleaſſes</cell>
                     <cell>200.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ships built after the Engliſh faſhion</cell>
                     <cell>120.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hulkes</cell>
                     <cell>020.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pinkes</cell>
                     <cell>020.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Catches</cell>
                     <cell>020.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In all</cell>
                     <cell>330.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15443:10"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Land Souldiers</cell>
                     <cell>60000.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Noblemen and Gentlemen being</cell>
                     <cell>8000.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Voluntaries</cell>
                     <cell>8000.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Saylers</cell>
                     <cell>13000.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Great Peeces of Ordnance</cell>
                     <cell>70.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Poyſoned Bullets for Ordnance</cell>
                     <cell>47000.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hollow Bullets filled with wild-fire</cell>
                     <cell>20000.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muskets and Caleeuers</cell>
                     <cell>12000.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Partizans</cell>
                     <cell>1000.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides double Cannons, field Peeces: dry-fats filled with old Nayles, and broken Iron, ſtore of Carriages: neceſſaries for Sea and Land, without number, three thouſand Speares, Armours of Musket-proofe, Wines, Biskets, Bacon, Cheeſe, Beefe, Rice, Beanes, Peaſe, Oyle, Lampes, Pipes for freſh water, Torches, Candles, Lanthornes, Hides, large Hogſheads, Wheele-barrowes, Wheeles, Spades, Mattocks, Shouels, Galthrops, Baskets, Boygh-ropes innumerable, and thirtie thouſand Pikes pointed with Iron.</p>
            <p>The Commanders of this Fleete are to meete with <hi>Spinola,</hi> who is to bee Generall of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>With <hi>Spinola,</hi> come <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Argile,</hi> with a great number of Horſes, and are to be tranſported in flat Boats.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> his Sonne is Admirall of the Spaniſh, Sir <hi>Robert Dudley</hi> Reare Admirall: Sir <hi>Griffin Markham,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> Colonels of the Regiments, and one <hi>Neuill</hi> who termes
<pb facs="tcp:15443:10"/>himſelfe Earle of <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> hath likewiſe a great command.</p>
            <p>There are lately arriued at Liſbone twentie ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Elephants from Perſia, for what imployment tis incertaine.</p>
            <p>And this is the moſt remarkable Newes of this Fleet; of which the Turke is ſo iealous, that hee ſtands vpon his guard.</p>
            <p>With ſo much does a Letter ſent from Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles acquaint vs, but from Malaga come theſe tydings. That there was neuer ſuch warlike prouiſion and preparation as is now in Spaine: Wine, Oyle, and Vineger to a great quantitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made readie with ten thouſand barrels of ſmall ſhot, a thouſand Kintals, ſixe thouſand Breames, or Bottels, ſixe thouſand Baskets for Pioners, with an incredible number of Spades, Shouels, Scoops, and Mattocks, with powder and wild-fire.</p>
            <p>From Dunkirke and other places in the Net her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands vnder the King of Spaine, are expected eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhips to be ayders in this great Expedition.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ships, theſe are prouided.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Auero</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Valencia</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Lisbone</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Guinny</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Cales</hi> and <hi>Auero</hi> Poole</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15443:11"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In Saint <hi>Sebaſtians</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Naples</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In <hi>Barcelon</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>240.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Malaga thus (as Marſeilles did before) hauing thundred out her ſtory of vproares and threatned deuaſtation: Here ſteps in a third Trumpetter, and proclaymes other newes, ſounding as harſhly as the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Fredericke</hi> of <hi>Toledo</hi> is generall of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by Sea, and the Marqueſſe by land, who hath vowed to lay his bones in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Generall of the Cauallery, is <hi>Don Carolo</hi> of <hi>Columbo:</hi> Commiſſions being granted to leuy three thouſand Horſe, aſwell Burgonians, as Lorrainers, and ſome out of Luremberg.</p>
            <p>If the Peace be made in Italy, the greateſt part of theſe Forces, are to goe by Sea, and ſo to fall into the Spaniſh Army, which is to ſet forth on the firſt of Iuly.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Spaniſh <hi>Leaders and their Companies.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Fuentes</hi> hath a Regiment of tenne Companies.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Don Ferdinando</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Don Diego</hi> of</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Coronell <hi>Bayard</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15443:11"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marqueſſe of <hi>Beluedore</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Three hundred men being in euery Company, which in the fiue Regiments, amount to 15000. beſides two other Regiments, the names of whoſe Coronels, I haue forgotten; ſo that the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my conſiſteth of one and twentie thouſand.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Italian <hi>Leaders.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pedro Aldobrandino</hi> Companies</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marqueſſe of <hi>Gonzales</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pedro</hi> of <hi>Gonzales</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>Don Carolo Spinola</hi> commands all the Italians.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The common rumour is, that they intend their courſe for Ireland; but the moſt knowing, ſay for England, the Dunkerkers (as it is reported) hauing ſownded all the Sea-coaſt, and aſſuring them an entrance free from all danger.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all the Engines and warlike furniture, which comes alongwith them, they alſo bring ſtore of Ouens, and Mils made of Iron or Braſſe, and will make their iſſue by the motion of wheeles, on which they are mounted.</p>
            <p>Thus this great Archer of the World (whoſe Bow reacheth from the Eaſt to the Weſt Indies, and whoſe ſtring is twiſted together by the Hands and Hearts of Confederated Kings and Princes) ſhoots his Arrowes at this our Kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, making account to come and cleane the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:15443:12"/>of it, and then to march backe into Spaine as a Triumphant Conquerour.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Nimrod</hi> is a mightie Hunter, and by his good will, would ſtrike downe none but whole Nations: Hauocke hee cryes what Parke ſo euer hee comes into; and the goodlier the Herds are, the more cruelly does hee ſcatter them. Millions of poore murthered Indians being the Trophies of his bloudy Shambles.</p>
            <p>But as the beginning of the firſt <hi>Nimrods</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, was Babell, ſo the end of this ſecond (Gods Almightie Arme tumbling downe the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of his Ambition) ſhall bee Confuſion.</p>
            <p>What though fiue Kings complot, combine, and incorporate their Forces in One, to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ioſua?</hi> Let not vs feare, but ſend vp our Cries to Heauen, as the Men of Gibeon (a great and Royall Citie) ſent theirs to <hi>Ioſua,</hi> euen to the Hoſt at Gilgall, and as they to Him, ſo let vs call to God, and ſay, <hi>Withdraw not thy Hand from thy Seruants; Come vp to vs quickly, and ſaue vs, and helpe vs;</hi> for all the Kings of the Amorites (Spinolized and Spaniolized Tyrants) thine and our Enemies, which dwell in the Mountaines, are gathered together againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt ſhake off our ſinnes when wee doe thus, and not cry with a faint and diſtruſting voyce that hee will not heare vs, for if we ſpeake to him as wee ought to doe, Hee himſelfe will
<pb facs="tcp:15443:12"/>ſay thus to our <hi>Ioſhua; Feare them not, for I haue giuen them into thine hand: None of them ſhall ſtand against thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the Lord kept his Word with Him, ſo will hee with vs: Hee will ſmite theſe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagued Enemies to his Truth and Goſpell, <hi>euen to Azekah, and Makkedah,</hi> (their Gibraltars and Magellanes) and as they are chaſed to Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horon (into Spaine) hee will (for their poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Bullets prepared to ſhoote at vs) caſt downe great ſtones from Heauen vpon them, vntill more dye by that haile, then by the ſword.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall theſe Confederated Kings of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Hebron, Iarmuth, Lachiſh and Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, flye to their Caues (their Spaniſh Dens) vntill the Chiefe Men of this our Iſraell by our <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> command, fetch them forth to ſet their feete vpon the neckes of ſuch inſolent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulters.</p>
            <p>Shall I reade to you, another ſtory of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? Hearken then to it.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Benhadad</hi> the King of Aram, had aſſembled all his Armie, with two and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Kings to aſſiſt him, hauing great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers both of Horſes and warlike Chariots, hee beſieged Samaria; and ſending a diſdainfull meſſage to <hi>Ahab</hi> King of Iſraell, thus hee commanded thoſe that went to terrifie him, Tell <hi>Ahab</hi> (quoth hee) <hi>that thy gold is Mine, alſo thy women and thy faire Children are Mine; or
<pb facs="tcp:15443:13"/>elſe, I will ſend my ſeruants vnto thee</hi> (as the King of Spaine would now his <hi>Ianizaries</hi> into England) <hi>and they ſhall ſearch thine Houſe, and the Houſes of thy Seruants, and whatſoeuer is pleaſing in thine eyes, they ſhall take it in their hands, and bring it away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Ahab</hi> taking Counſell of the Elders, did at the ſecond ſending, refuſe to part from any thing.</p>
            <p>Herevpon <hi>Benhadad</hi> in a rage fel a rauing, and ſaid, <hi>The Gods do ſo to me, and more alſo, if the dust of Samaria, be enough to all the people that follow me, for euery man a handfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poore Samaria was now in a terrible feare, <hi>Benhadad</hi> roared, Iſraell trembled: but God caſting an Eye of Compaſſion vpon their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, and an Eye of Scorne on the others tyrannies, ſent a Prophet to <hi>Ahab,</hi> who told him this good tydings (after one Army ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne by <hi>Ahab</hi> the yeere before) <hi>I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer this great multitude into thy hands again, and yee ſhall know that I am the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His word was true, the children of Iſraell ſtood in the field in the day of Battaile <hi>like two little flockes of Kiddes, but the Aramites coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the whole Countrey:</hi> yet the poore Handfull had the victory: the Sheepe beate the Lions, and ſlue in that day a hundred thouſand Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites (all footmen.)</p>
            <p>It is not Number that preuailes, but good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:15443:13"/>of the Cauſe. When Iuſtice guardes the Standard, Safetie is Generall of the Field.</p>
            <p>No matter what proud defiance, a daring <hi>Philistine</hi> throwes into our faces, there is an Arme Omnipotent can direct a Peeble-ſtone (beeing but put into a Sling) to ſticke in the Giants fore-head, both to ſtrike him dead, and confound the whole Armie that comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him.</p>
            <p>Regard not the Braues of a blaſpheming <hi>Rabſhecay</hi> ſent from <hi>Senacherib</hi> King of Aſhur, to the Cities of Iuda, For a voyce from the mouth of the God of Hoſts, ſhall come to an <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> ſaying thus much. <hi>As for Aſhur, Hee ſhall not enter into this Citie, nor ſhoote an Arrow at it, nor come before it with a Shield, nor cast a Mount against it; but hee ſhall returne the way he came, and ſhall not come into this Citie.</hi> What followed vpon this comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble promiſe? <hi>The ſame night, the Angell went out, and ſmote in the Campe of Aſhur, one hundred foureſcore and fiue thouſand men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Senacherib</hi> eſcaped from the ſlaughter, but not from Gods vengeance; for afterwards, as in his Temple be was worſhipping <hi>Niſrech</hi> (his God) <hi>Adramelech,</hi> and <hi>Sharezer his owne Sonnes, ſlew him with the ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Examples to this purpoſe may bee brought into the Field, of infinite Armies, of Idolatrous Nations fighting againſt Iuda and
<pb facs="tcp:15443:14"/>Iſraell, and yet were then ſtill (ſo long as they held in with God) by weake and waſted troupes confounded.</p>
            <p>For, God hath ſtill a Red Sea to ſtand vp an end on either ſide of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Iſraelites like a double Brazen wall to guard his people, but to fall downe in rough billowes, to ouerwhelme <hi>Pharao</hi> and his Hoſt.</p>
            <p>Yet wee muſt not preſume too much vpon Gods fauour, as if we were his onely Darlings, and all other Nations, Caſt-awayes. No there is no ſuch excellence in vs, that hee ſhould dote vpon our beautie, which is nothing elſe but a lothſome Deformitie.</p>
            <p>We haue beene ſcourged lately, with one of <hi>Dauids</hi> whips, but the Beating is forgotten, and therefore we were beſt take heed, leſt this ſecond Rod drawes bloud indeed. Our ſinnes are in our hearts, when our ſwords are in our hands, and the muſtering of the One, frights vs from ſtriking with the other. Turne away the firſt, and God will teach vs how to turne the ſecond vpon the boſomes of our Enemies.</p>
            <p>It is folly to goe into the field to fight, vnleſſe God ſends out his Prieſt, to haue vs ſerue vnder his Colours: Let vs take his pay and wee muſt needs prooue Noble Souldiers: Euery Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man make but peace with his owne Conſcience, and be carefull that it betrayes him not, and hee needs not feare any Spaniſh Inuaſion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15443:14"/>
            <p>Spaniſh Inuaſion! Theſe Thunderings and Lightnings, may bee but Terrors talked of, and not ſeene: or if ſeene, not certainly ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming where to doe miſchiefe: they may hurt others ſooner then Vs: Theſe Spaniſh Canons, happily carrie no Bullets in them, but giue one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a falſe fire.</p>
            <p>Theſe Rumours and Tumours, Whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds, Vproares and Combuſtions, filling the Chriſtian World with Amazement, and vs with expectation of ſome dreadfull Monſter to bee preſented to all wondring eyes, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance bring forth onely That ridiculous Mouſe, of which the Mountaynes were ſo long in labour.</p>
            <p>It is well, if it bee ſo: The <hi>Beati Pacifici</hi> is a ſtring which makes heauenly Muſicke in a Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Yet, if wee lift vp our heads, to obſerue what eyes the Spaniard caſts at vs, and what good Prayers he ſhoots after vs; Wiſdome may ſoone perſwade, that hee does not loue vs; if not loue vs, wee are not to truſt Him, (albeit hee lyes ſtill) no more then to truſt a ſleeping Lion or a Maſtiffe: and therefore (not to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle our ſelues too much vpon the knees of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie) let vs rowſe vp our Engliſh Spirits, and bee armed, againſt this ſpotted Beaſt doe come, albeit hee bee not comming, leſt with his pawes hee teare vs in pieces, when wee are
<pb facs="tcp:15443:15"/>not prouided for his dreadfull Encounters.</p>
            <p>Spaniſh Bulles are fierce at the ſtake, and worſe looſe, and although in Madrill, Siuill, and others Cities, they baite them for pleaſure, in England they would yeeld no ſuch paſtime. If Fame therefore, hath taught her thouſand Tongues to tell Truth, and that theſe Caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Ecchoes mocke vs not with Lyes, Is it not high time for euery man to girt his loynes with the ſword, and to fight Gods Battaile, for this Quarrell is againſt Him?</p>
            <p>If this holy League be knit together, to teare Anointed Kings, out of their hereditary thrones, and to turne Nations out of their Natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; It is not a Holy, but a Deuilliſh League: A Confederacie of vncleane Spirits: An Vnion of Diſcord, and Helliſh Muſicke.</p>
            <p>Let thoſe then, who haue commands ouer Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Seas (whoſe Nurſing Armes moſt louingly embrace our Kingdomes body, buſie themſelues in their Nauall-Military Preparations; whileſt they on Land muſter together to guard our Kingdomes Heart.</p>
            <p>Let our Engliſh Nobles giue Heroicall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frontations to the Spaniſh <hi>Grandees</hi> and <hi>Dons:</hi> the Gentry hearten on the Commons, and the Commons goe with cheerfull faces, againſt this Enemie, as their Fore-fathers haue done, when they fetched Honour from other Countries.</p>
            <p>Whileſt the Diuine prayes at home, for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb facs="tcp:15443:15"/>abroad: whilſt the Lawyer ſpends ſome of his Golden Fees, to the maintenance of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, in ſo glorious a warre: whileſt Citizens open bounteous Purſes, (though they goe not in Perſon) to defend themſelues, and Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: whileſt the ſtrong runne to fight, and the weake looke to their Houſes at home: whilſt the Rich emptie their bagges, to maintaine the poore Souldiers in good clothes and wholſome diet: Nay, whileſt euen the very Blinde and Lame (when they can doe nothing elſe) ſend vp their heartie wiſhes to Heauen (night and day) to crowne our Land with Conqueſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all bloudie and execrable Confederations with ruine and ſhame, and to ſend home this ſecond Armipotent Armado (if any ſuch there be) in Tempeſts, Whirle-winds and Wracks, as that was in Eighty eight. To which all true hearted Engliſhmen will crie <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
